ok so for this problem we've got a
substrate here which has a ketone
functional group and a carboxylic acid
functional group and we're gonna do two
reactions with two different reducing
agents, we've got sodium borohydride and
we've got lithium aluminum hydride so if
you don't remember what these do go ahead and
check out my lecture on oxidation
reduction in the organic chemistry
playlist and we we these are going to
generate two different products based on
reducing capacity of these two reducing
agents so go and see if you can draw the
correct product for these two
transformations
we've got our two different reducing agents, our sodium
borohydride and a lithium
aluminum hydride, we know that those are
both sources of hydride, H- which is
going to act as a nucleophile and
attack a carbonyl and reduce some carbonyl
containing compound but the key
difference here is that sodium
borohydride is a softer reducing agent, a
bit weaker whereas lithium aluminum
hydride is a hard reducing agent, it's a little
bit stronger, so there is a
discrepancy in what kind of carbonyl
containing compounds they are able to
reduce. as it happens sodium borohydride is
only able to reduce ketones and
aldehydes, this is because the ketone
an aldehyde functional group, the partial
positivity on this carbonyl carbon
differs from that of say a carboxylic
acid because this carbon there, remember
that this adjacent oxygen atom is able to
put electrons onto that carbon via
resonance and so that is the reason that
this is not as partially positive and
therefore not as electrophilic as a ketone
or aldehyde carbon so that means that
just the discrepancy in electrophilicity
between this and this means that sodium
borohydride is able to reduce this
ketone functional group but not the
carboxylic acid functional group so as a
result on the product
reducing with sodium borohydride we can
see that the ketone has been reduced to
the secondary alcohol whereas the
carboxylic acid has been untouched
it does not have the ability to reduce the
carboxylic acid so that won't change
however lithium aluminum hydride is able
to reduce ketones, aldehydes, carboxylic
acids, esters, it is a stronger reducing
agent because it's stronger it is
able to reduce not just this but also
this and so as a result we can see in
the product that the ketone has been
reduced to the secondary alcohol just as
it has over here but in addition the
carboxylic acid has been reduced to the
primary alcohol. so the key here is
noticing the difference in reducing
strength of these two reducing agents and
using that information to draw the to
correct products
thanks for watching guys, subscribe to my
channel for more tutorials and as always
feel free to email me